[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Thirty]
[第三十集]
Yannian. Qiaonian.
延年 乔年
I need you two for a mission.
我要抓你们一个差
I just wrote an article.
我刚刚写了一篇文章
The title is
题目是
"Inform all people about the Shandong issue"
《为山东问题敬告各方面》
This article is written for the general strike tomorrow.
这篇文章是为了明天总罢课写的
It aims to warn everyone out there.
主要是想告大家
Don't think the Shandong issue
千万不要以为山东问题
is just a matter of the survival of one province.
仅仅是一个省的存亡问题
It's not just a matter for academics.
也不光是学界一家的事情
It is an incoming danger for the whole China.
而是全中国的事情
Whoever you are, academics, politicians or businessmen
无论学界 政界 商人
farmers, labors, police or soldiers
农夫 劳工 警察 当兵的
bureaucratics, congressman or journalist
做官的 议员 新闻记者
All of you have to come forward.
全都要站出来
This arrow of the national movement should point at
国民斗争的矛盾
the traitorous government
应该指向卖国政府
It shall not be like May 4th.
而不要再像五月四日那样
Cao Rulin Zhang, Zongxiang and Lu Zongyu
仅仅限于曹汝霖 章宗祥
Those traitors is not the sole target.
陆宗舆那几个卖国贼
To make sure everyone sees this
为了让明天大家游时
tomorrow during the protest.
都能看到这篇文章
We must print it out today.
我们今天一定要把它油印出来
You okay doing this?
你们愿意吗
Sure.
愿意
Okay, go to the Red House Library of Peking University.
好去北大红楼图书馆
Ask Shouchang to get mimeograph and paper.
找守常把油印机和纸张拿来
We'll print it right here
我们就在这儿印
Cherish our nation, protect our country.
爱我中华 保卫中国
Please take a look.
您看一下
This is my year 1919.
这是我的一九一九
My 1919
我的一九一九
It's also every Chinese's year 1919.
是中国人的一九一九
And the peace between North and South is broken.
而破环南北之和议
Us students...
学生等之
We shall never sign this treaty.
欧会不得签字
But now the Japanese comes, claims they have the power.
可是现在日本人要来当我们的家
They want to be our master.
要来做我们的主
This letter in my hand
我手中的这封信
It's a declaration to our President Xu Shichang.
是致我们大总统徐世昌的宣言
Can we let it happen?
咱们能同意吗
No, no, no
不能 不能 不能
Please support our declaration.
请大家支持我们的宣言
Support us
支持宣言
Why are we launching this student movement?
支持宣高
Punish the traitors!
惩办国贼
Simply changing the signboard from old Qing times
仅仅是把大清朝门头上的牌扁
to a new one written in China gate is not enough.
换成了中华门
Such revolution is not complete and thorough.
这样的革命并不彻底
Cao Rulin, Zhang Zongxiang and Lu Zongyu
曹汝霖 章宗祥 陆宗
these three owe their lives to us people.
国人皆可杀
Bring Cai Yuanpei back.
挽回蔡元培
Cherish our nation, protect our country.
爱我中华 保卫祖国
My fellow worker friends.
广大的工人朋友们
Today, I want to tell you about
今天 我想给大家讲一讲
the Paris Peace Treaty.
巴黎和约的事
Back in the Qing Dynasty, our Qingdao was occupied.
咱们的中国青岛在清朝的时候
The Germans took it by force.
让德国人强行霸占了
Now, Germany was defeated this world war.
这次世界大战 德国人打败了
We are one of the victorious countries.
我们是战胜国
Before, we couldn't fight back Germany's gunfire.
原先因为我们打不过德压
We had no choice but to let them took Qingdao.
没办法 青岛让给他们了
But now
但是现在
We defeated Germany.
我们把德国打败了
Qingdao should be returned to us.
青岛应该归还给我们
This is a matter of course, right?
这是天经地义的事 对吗
right
对
good
好
But, Japan came out.
这个时候日本出来说话了
They say that
它说
Our government of the Republic of China wanted to borrow money from Japan.
我们的民国政府为了向它借钱
So they agreed that
曾经答应过
The administration of Qingdao would be handed over to Japan.
要把青岛的管理权交给日本
America, France and UK on the Paris Peace Conference
巴黎和会的美压 法国 英国
They dare not provoke Japan, so they went along with it.
不敢得罪日本也就同意了
Friends, if that's the case,
工友们 如果这样一来的话
this country, as a victorious country,
我们这个战胜国
not only did we not have any gain from our victory,
不光什么都没得到
instead of Qingdao's return,
反而把应该归还给我们的青岛
we are losing it to Japan.
转交给了日本
I'd like you to think it over.
我想请大家好好想一想
This is our business.
这是我们中国人自己的事情
However,
可是这件事
We Chinese people can't make decisions by ourselves.
我们中国人自己做不了主
Instead, those foreigners somehow has that power.
反倒交给外国人做主
Is this axiom?
这个叫公理吗
Defend China's sovereignty to death!
死捍卫中国主权
Even more exasperating is that
更可气的是
our government actually agreed on
这么一个丧权辱国的条约
such a treaty deeply disgraces our country.
我们的政府居然同意了
The government agreed to sign it!
居然答应签字了
My fellow worker friends, this country is called the Republic of China.
工友们咱们是民国呀
What is the Republic of China?
什么是民国
It means the people's country.
民国就是人民的国家
I'd like to ask you, is there any important issue
任何一件大事 我想问问大家
where our opinions are valued?
问过你们的意见吗
We, the working class.
我们这群工友们
Bleeding, sweating and working hard every day.
每天流着血 流看汗拼命工作
Created so much wealth for the country.
为国家创造了那么多的财富
I want to ask everyone
我想问问大家
Have you been consulted on important state affairs?
国家大事征求过你们的意见了吗
No, no.
没有 没有 没有
Since the founding of the Republic of China
自打这个民国成立以来
so many ridiculous things have happened.
发生了那么多荒唐的事
What's the one thing that makes you masters of your own affairs?
哪一件事是让你们当家做主了
No.
没有 没有
We're just a bunch of coolies.
我们就是一群下苦力的臭力巴
Be looked down upon
被人看不起
We don't even get enough food.
我们吃饭都吃不饱
We are not our own masters.
我们不是主人
No, no
不是主人 不是主人
Why are the students taking it to the streets?
学生们上街游行为的是什么
They are boycotting this shameless peace treaty.
为的就是抵制这个无耻的和约
They are defending China's sovereignty.
为的是捍卫我们中国的主权
They are exercising their rights,
为的是要行使我们中国人
the rights as a Chinese citizen to have a say in this country.
当中国家的权利
Workers
工友们
We are all people with a patriotic heart.
我们都是有一颗爱国心的人
China is our Chinese's China.
中国是我们中国人的中国
Our own country
我们自己的国家
Who else than us would love and cherish it?
我们不爱 谁爱
right
对
So,
所以
We can't just stand by and watch
对于学生们这么一个爱国行为
this patriotic act of the students.
我们绝不能袖手旁观
We can't ignore it.
置之不理呀
Pledge to defend China's sovereignty!
誓死捍卫中国主权
Defend China's sovereignty to death!
死捍卫中国主权
Shandong issue is not only the survival of a province.
山东问题不是一个省的存亡问题
It's a national problem.
而是全国的问题
Whoever you are, academics or politicians,
无论是学界政界
Merchants, laborers, farmers, police
商人劳工 农夫 警察
A member of parliament or a soldier,
当兵的 做官的议员
or journalists , everyone has to come forward.
新闻记者 都要站出来
If we don't,
我们不站出来
who will stand up and help us?
谁能站出来帮我们
China is my China.
中国是我的中国
It's also your China.
也是你的中国
China
中国
is Chinese's China.
是中国人的中国
Students.
同学
I want to say a few words.
我想说两句
good
好
Fellow citizens
同胞们
I am Shen Deling, I work in a textile company.
我是纺织公司
I am the director of the office manages monopoly right of our Spinning Jenny machine.
纺纱机专卖处处长沈德铃
Students' patriotic enthusiasm
同学们的爱国热情
touched me deeply.
深深地感化了我
Now I'm willing to give what I hold in my hand to the public,
现在我愿意将手中持有的
the exclusive right of spinning machine is open to everyone.
纺纱机专卖权公开让给国人
So that our country's strength is empowered.
以强我国力
Bravo!
好
Make the way.
散开 散开
Go away.
散开
What are you doing!
千什么
What are you doing
干什么
Stop!
住手
You all stop!
你们都住手
What you're wearing on your heads
你们头上戴的
Isn't it a Chinese hat?
难道不是中国的帽子吗
The soil you stepped on right now.
你们脚下踩的
Isn't it Chinese land?
难道不是中国的土地吗
What you eat, drink, wear and use.
你们吃的喝的 穿的用的
Which one is not the blood and sweat of the people?
哪一个不是人民的血汗
Why when we are making speech for everyone,
为什么我辈为了你们而演讲
you guys?
而你们呢
You are pushing us away for the enemy.
却在替敌人来驱赶我们
You might be wearing police caps.
你们这些头戴警帽
But you are merely idiots holding a police sticks now, wake up!
手拿警棍的糊涂虫 醒醒吧
Even if you don't care for the country's survival
即使不为了国家谋生存
can't you think it over just for the sake of you and your family?
也应该为了自己和家人的活路
Think about it.
想一想啊
We students come forward calling for justice.
我们学生站出来
What did we do wrong?
我们做错了什么
We did nothing wrong.
我们没做错
Take Shandong Qingdao back!
收复山东青岛主权
Release the arrested students!
释放被捕学生
Punish the traitors!
严卖国贼
Teachers, students.
老师们同学们
Today, we Xinmin Association
今天 我们新民学会
gathered representatives from more than 20 schools in Changsha here.
把长沙的二十多所学校的代表
We would like to call for
就是和大家一起
our support of Beijing's May 4th Movement together.
协商声援北京的五四运动
Urge the government to boycott the Paris Peace Treaty
敦促政府 抵制巴黎和约
This ..
这位
Is the head of Peking University Student Union.
是北京大学学生会的负责人
Mr. Deng Zhongxia.
邓中夏先生
He was entrusted by Mr. Chen Duxiu
他是受陈独秀先生
and Mr. Li Dazhao
李大钊先生的委托
to come to Changsha for support.
到长沙寻求支援
Next, he will tell us
下面 我请他
about the situation in Beijing.
为我们介绍一下北京的情况
Good
好好
Teachers!
各位老师
Fellow students
各位同学
My name is Deng Zhongxia.
我叫邓中夏
Being here today
今天我来到这里
seeing everyone
看到大家
I feel really nostalgic.
我非常亲切
Because
因为我本人啊
I am a native of Hunan.
就是土生土长的湖南人
So today
所以今天
I'm home.
我回家了
Welcome home!
欢迎回家
I want to thank the Xinmin Association led by Mao Zedong.
我要感谢毛泽东领导的新民学会
Thank you all
感谢诸位
for your support towards the Beijing Federation of Students
对我们北京学联
and the support of Peking University Student Union.
和北大学生会的支持
thank you
谢谢
The current situation in Beijing
现在北京的情况
is very exhilarating.
很是令人振奋
But at the same time
但同时
also full of crisis.
也充满了危机
Now the people in Beijing
现在北京民众的力量
and the Beiyang government
和北洋政府的力量
is in the middle of a fierce confrontation.
正在进行激烈的对
What we should do now
而我们现在应该做的
is to stick to it.
就是要坚持下去
We should mobilize the efforts of the whole nation.
我们要举全国民众之力
We should team up with every Chinese.
我们要举全民族之力
And keep fighting to the end.
来将这场斗争坚持到底
Us Beijing Federation of Students
我们北京学联
and Peking University Student Union
还有北大学生会
have organized more than twenty rally groups.
已经组织了二十多个宣讲团
They will go to all provinces and cities in the country to preach.
到全国的各个省市去宣讲
I came to Changsha, Hunan.
而我来到了咱们湖南长沙
I'd like to invite all of you
我想请诸位
My brothers
我的兄长
My classmates
我的同学们
My brothers and sisters.
我的兄弟姐妹们
Please join this fight with us.
请和我们掀起一场
Join this patriotic movement throughout the whole nation.
全民族的爱国运动
To save us,
来拯救我们
to save our motherland on the verge of collapse.
频临崩溃的祖国
Okay, okay, okay.
好好好
Zhongxie.
仲
I want to know.
我想知道
What is this campaign aiming to achieve?
这次运动要达到什么冒的
Is there a specific goal?
有没有一个具体的目标
To urge the government to refuse to sign the Paris Peace Treaty.
促使政府拒签巴黎和约
To never give Qingdao to Japan.
绝不能把青岛让给日本
What we have to do now
我们现在要做的
is to awaken the whole nation.
就是唤起全民族的觉醒
We want to transform the whole society.
我们要改造全社会
We want to make it happen that
我们要让劳动者
the working class become the master of the country.
成为天下的主人
Great.
好好好
Good point!
说得好
Students.
同学们
I brought you something.
我给大家带来了一些东西
These are the  established by
这些是陈独秀先生和李大钊先生
Mr. Chen Duxiu and Mr. Li Dazhao.
所主办的 《每周评论》
You can learn more about the latest situation in Beijing
从中可以更加了解
and our lateset ideas
北京最新的情况
from this paper.
和我们最新的主张
Students,
同学们
please send this out.
把这发一下
come
来
Pass it around to each other.
大家互相传阅一下
Pass it around, everybody.
各位传着看看
You can use this Weekly Review
大家可以通过这个 《每周评论》
to learn about the latest situation in Beijing.
来了解我们京的最新情况
Look, this is the paper from Beijing.
你看这就是北京那杂志
How can Shandong be given to the Japanese?
山东怎么能让给日本人
We must fight to the end. Yeah
一定要斗争到底对
classmates
同学们
Everyone saw it.
大家都看到了
Mr. Chen Duxiu's slogan
陈独秀先生的口号
All people stand up
就是全体人民站起来
to solve the problem directly.
直接地解决问题
We Hunan
我们湖南
Can't fall behind.
也不能落后
So,
所以
on behalf of Xinmin Association, I propose
我代表新民学会提议
to set up Hunan Students Federation fast.
迅速成立湖南学生联合会
Launch a general strike of students in the whole province.
发动全省学生总罢课
At the same time,
同时
contact all parties in Hunan urgently.
紧急联络湖南各界
Establish Hunan Federation of all walks of life
成立湖南各界联合会
Achieve the great unity of the people
实现民众的大联合
Good
好好好
I support the strike.
我支持罢课
Runzhi
润之
Us Hunan Commercial College
我们湖南商业专门学校
supports students to strike
支持学生罢课
But due to the lack of experience.
但是 由于大家缺乏经验
I suggest
我建议
that Xinmin Association should take the lead
由新民学会
on this people's grand coalition in the whole province.
承担起全省民众大联合的领导责任
You will take the responsibility.
你要多担待
With no hesitations.
责无旁贷
For better guidance
为了更好地指导
of Hunan's patriotic movement
湖南的爱国运动
I suggest
我建议
that we should follow Beijing's example.
我们应该效仿北京的做法
Hunan Federation of Students should also
由湖南省学联
run a magazine.
也办一本杂志
It's called
名字就叫
Good!
好啊
This is good.
这个好啊
just right
正好
An echo of Beijing's Weekly Review.
可以跟北京的《每周评论》
Echo each other
相互呼应起来
Runzhi
润之
That's a great idea.
你这个主意太好了
Our May 4th Movement in Beijing was guided
我们北京的五四运动啊
by the Weekly Review.
就是在《每周评论》的
Mr. Zhongfu will publish several articles in each issue.
仲甫先生每期会发表好几篇文章
He is our commander in chief.
他就是我们的总司令
I think Xiangjiang Review
我觉得 《湘江评论》
Should also play such a role.
也应该发挥这样的作用
Right
对
As for the editor-in-chief
至于主编嘛
Runzhi
润之
None but you
非你莫属
Fellow students
同学们
Mao Zedong is member of Journalism Research Association
毛泽东是北京大学
in Peking University.
新闻学研究会会员
I suggest
我建议
for the editor-in-chief of Xiangjiang Review
《湘江评论》 的主编
he should be the one.
就由他来担任
Agree?
大家同意吗
Agree
同意同意
Okay, okay, okay.
同意 同意
Classmates
同学们
I must
我一定
successfully fulfil this mission.
不辱使命
good
好
come
来
Come to the meeting.
来开会
Come, come, have a meeting.
来来来 开会了 开会了
Have a seat please.
请坐
Yes
好
Time for a meeting.
开会
Fellow students
同学们
I'd like to introduce two people to you.
我给大家介绍两位同学
This is Zhao Shiyan.
这位是赵世炎同学
He is the representative of Beijing Federation of Students.
是北京市学联代表
Entrusted by Chen Duxiu and Li Dazhao
受陈独秀和李大钊先生的委托
Come to our Federation for support.
来我们学联寻求支援的
This is Zhou Enlai.
这位是周恩来同学
Zhou Enlai just returned from studying in Japan.
周恩来同学刚从日本留学归来
He is the editor-of-chief
是我们即将创办的
of Tianjin Student Union Newspaper we are about to establish.
《天津学生联合会报》 的主编
Now
现在呢
Let's have Zhao Shitan
我们先请赵世炭同学
tell us about the situation in Beijing.
给我们介绍一下北京的情况
Beijing and Tianjin are as close as lips and teeth
京津一体 唇齿相依
The situation in Beijing is very urgent now.
北京现在的情况十分紧急
We need support from all over the country.
切需要全国各地的支持
Before the end of the month, the Beijing Federation of Students will organize
月底前 北京学联将会组织一次
large-scale demonstrations and petitions.
大规模的示威请愿活动
I hope all major cities in the country
希望全国各大城市
join us.
都参加
Firstly,
一方面
to demonstrate all Chinese students' determination
彰显全中国学生
in this patriotic movement.
爱国运动的气势和决心
Secondly, to prepare for the establishment of the National Federation of Students.
一方面 为成立全国学联做准备
This is also the purpose and mission of my visit here to Tianjin.
这也是我此次来天津的目的和使命
I brought some
我带来了一些
latest .
最新出版的 《每周评论》
From it you can read about
大家可以从中了解到
the current situation in Beijing and our ideas.
北京现在的情况和我们的主张
Fellow students
同学们
The Students Federation and our Women's Patriotic Association.
关于组织赴京请愿
have made arrangements for organizing petitions
和我们的女界爱国同志会
in Beijing.
已经做了安排
Next, Deng Wenshu please.
下面请邓文淑同学
An introduction.
给大家做介绍
The Tianjin delegation going for the petitions in Beijing this time
这次赴京请愿的天津代表团
will be led by Ma Jun and Liu Qingyang.
由马骏和刘清扬带队
All schools in Tianjin
我们天津各个学校
will send representatives to attend.
都将派出代表参加
To express
为了表达
our determination to fight till the end
我们与北京学界
together with Beijing academic circles
命运与共 战斗到底的决心
Our academic circles in Tianjin havs drafted an affidavit.
我们天津学界也起草了宣誓书
There are six articles altogether.
一共有六条
First, pledge to guard the motherland.
誓保国土
Second, pledge to protect the sovereignty.
誓挽国权
Third, pledge to wipe off national humiliation.
誓雪国耻
Fourth, pledge to rid the country of traitors.
誓除国贼
Fifth, pledge to face danger together.
五誓共安危
Sixth, pledge to always stand side by side.
六誓同始终
Any opinion is welcome.
请大家审议
Fellow students
同学们
For better guidance
为了更好地指导
our student movement in Tianjin.
我们天津的学生运动
We decided
我们决定
to follow Peking University's Weekly Review
效仿北大的 《每周评论》
Establish Tianjin Student Union Newspaper.
创办 《天津学生联合会报》
Given the fact that Zhou Enlai
鉴于周恩来同学呢
has established  and
以前在南开就主办过《校风》
in Nankai before.
和《敬业》 等刊物
He has rich experience in running journals.
有丰富的办刊经验
Through joint decision
学联决定
we hired Zhou Enlai
聘请周恩来同学
as our editor in chief.
为我们的主编
This is a difficult and bitter job.
这是一个又难又苦的差事
Comrade Enlai has been worked on this by himself
恩来同志一个人
for more than half a month.
奋斗了半个多月
The preparatory work for the Union Newspaper has been completed.
已经完成了会报的筹备工作
Now
下面呢
Let's invite Zhou Enlai.
我们就请周恩来同学
Give a brief introduction.
给大家做一个简单的介绍
Fellow students
各位同学
Soon after I came back
我回国不久
The May 4th Movement took place.
就赶上了五四运动
I am entrusted with an important task by the Student Federation.
学联委我以重任
Being editor-in-chief of Student Union Newspaper,
主编 《学生联合会报》
to me,
对我而言
is an unshirkable responsibility.
自然是义不容辞的责任
Based on
我们以北京的 《新青年》
and other papers in Beijing,
《每周评论》 《新潮》等
We made the preliminary draft
刊物为参考
focusing on advocating ideas and commenting on current politics.
以主张和时评为重点
We set up eight columns
设置了新思潮
including New Trend and New Idea
新动态等八个栏目
We also have 20 codes for running this paper.
和二十条办报宗旨
Mainly can be expressed in two sentences.
最主要是两句话
All proposals being released are based on the spirit of democracy.
本民主主义的精神发表一切主张
With the spirit of innovation for both our heart and mind as the main theme.
本革心同革新的精神立为主旨
We publicize new thoughts,
宣传新思潮
report and comment on current affairs both domestic and abroad.
报道和评论国内外时事
and the national student movement.
和全国学生运动
We will put forward the slogan for the grand scheme accordingly
根据天津和全国的形势
as the situation in Tianjin and the whole country keeps envolving.
及时提出斗争口号
To guide the broad masses of revolutionary youth
指导广大革命青年的
to fight against imperialism and warlords.
反帝反军阀的斗争
Chief editor Zhou
周主编
Can you tell us about
那你能不能跟我们说说
The difference between innovation for heart and for mind?
革新写革心的区别
Sure.
好
In brief,
简单地说
Innovation for our minds
革新呢
is to transform society.
就是要改造社会
Innovation for our hearts
而革心呢
is to transform our own ideology.
是改造我们自身的思想
The latter one is the premise and foundation of the former one.
革心是革新的前提和基础
Innovation is revolutionary.
革新是革心的的
I'm going to write an inaugural article for the paper
我准备以革新和革心为题
discussing these two innovations.
为会报写一篇创刊词
To call on the patriotic youth to consciously
号召广大爱国青年自觉地
combine transformation of one's own thoughts
把改造自身思想
and of the whole society.
同改造社会结合起来
Arm our spirits with the weapon of new trend and new thoughts
用世界新思潮 新思想
all round the world.
武装我们的精神
And to bring the people's consciousness back.
唤醒民众的觉悟
Unite people with such aspirations
把有这样志向的人团结起来
and achieve the fundamental transformation of Chinese society.
实现对中国社会的根本改造
Pledge to guard the motherland.
保国土
Pledge to wipe off national humiliation.
誓雪国耻
Pledge to rid the country of traitors.
除国贼
Pledge to face danger together.
共安危
Pledge to always stand side by side.
誓同始终
Zhou Enlai is here.
周恩来同学来了
Students, according to reliable information
同学们 根据可靠情报
Nankai, in exchange for donation funds,
南开学校为了换取捐助经费
has secretly arranged a deal with the traitor Cao Rulin.
已经私下与大卖国贼曹汝霖
They want to hire Cao Rulin as a board member of Nankai University.
欲聘请曹汝霖为南开大学校董
This is a utter disgrace to Nankai Univeristy.
这是南开的奇耻大辱
I propose, to defend the honor of Nankai
我提议为了捍卫南开的荣誉
We're going to raise a strong protest now.
我们现在就去向校方
We can never let the shameless traitor Cao Rulin
绝不能让大卖国贼曹汝霖
stained the glory of Nankai.
站污了南开的光荣
Yes.
好
Students, come with me.
同学们 跟我来
Go
走
Pledge to guard the motherland.
誓保国土
Pledge to protect the sovereignty.
誓挽国权
Pledge to wipe off national humiliation.
誓雪国耻
Pledge to rid the country of traitors.
誓除国贼
Gentlemen
列位
I was entrusted by the President,
我受大总统委托
to host this meeting on his behalf.
代其主持本次会议
Chen Lu reported yesterday that
昨日 陈篆报告说
Japanese Ambassador Obada
日本公使小罐
made a strong protest to us.
向我提出强烈抗议
He demanded us to treat students
要求我方对学生
in a way more courageous and dominant.
拿出点勇气 霸气来
This morning
今日早上
The president spoke to Duan Qirui on the phone.
大总统和段祺瑞通了电话
Said that students in Tsinghua University and some other schools.
说清华大学和一些学校的学生
Instead of attending classes, they now practice martial arts.
不上课 改练武了
It's having a very bad influence.
影响很坏
This month only, we have held more than a dozen meetings
本月以来 就学生的问题
regarding the student issue.
我们已经开了十几次会议了
Director Wu
吴总监
Please update everyone on the situation.
请你把情况跟大家说一下吧
My friends, it's getting worse and worse.
老几位 问题越来越严重了
It's not just students now.
不光是学生啊
All walks of life are involved to certain extents.
各阶层都有不同程度的卷入
It's also not just Beijing.
不光是北京
All the major cities in the country are making a fuss.
全国各大中心城市都闹起来了
This kind of involvement of the whole society.
全社会的卷入
It is unprecedented.
这可是前所未有的事情啊
Merchants and laborers in Beijing are also onto something,
北京的商人和劳工也蠢欲动
there is a tendency they will join hands with students.
大有和学生联手之趋势
In the May 4th Movement,
五四的时候
students only proposed to severely punish the traitors.
学生们只是提出要严惩卖国贼
But now,
可现在倒好
they are aiming at the government directly.
直接指向了政府
If we don't take tough actions
如果在这个时候
now
不采取强硬的行动
This chaotic situation will surely start a prairie fire.
那这乱局势必成燎原之势
Spread rapidly throughout China.
迅速传遍中国
Director Wu
吴总监
According to you.
照你的说法
The student movement has already spread all over the country .
学生的运动已经蔓延到全国了
What tough measures are you going to take?
那你打算采取什么强硬法
Toughness means that students can't be doing whatever they want.
强硬就是对学生不能听之任之
Arrest when needed and sentence when needed.
该抓的抓 该判的判
Resolutely perform the functions of the government.
坚决履行政府的职能
I don't agree.
你的意见我不敢苟同
I think the root of this mess
我认为这次乱局的根子
is the dismissal of Cai Yuanpei.
就在于蔡元培的出走
If we find a way
如果我们想办法
to bring Cai Yuanpei back,
把蔡元培给请回来
have the students of Peking University managed by Cai Yuanpei,
北大的学生照样归蔡元培管
it'll be much better than using force.
这样比动武要好得多
Besides, the cost and loss are much smaller.
而且这样成本和损失也小得多呀
You are only focusing on one end.
你这是剃头挑子一头热啊
You should know that
你又不是不知道
those professors
祭元培身边那些
the ones advocating the new culture movement around Cai Yuanpei.
鼓吹新文化运动的教授
They are the behind-the-scenes commander of this mess.
正是这场乱局的幕后指挥者
Ask them to help ease the situattion is a ridiculous move.
请他们帮助政府平息乱后
Nonsense, you might as well daydreaming.
无异于痴人说梦 与虎谋皮
What did you say, nonsense?
什么叫与虎谋皮啊
Is that your attitude?
什么态度你是
Yes, you have a problem?
我就是这个态度 怎么着
Every one.
列位 列位
Shut up
闭嘴
What do you want?
你要千什么
Student movement is no small matter.
学生运动非同小可
General Duan and the President had a long call in the morning.
早上大师和大总统
They have given due thoughts about this.
通了很长时间的电话 酌再三
And they decided to take tough actions first.
决定先来硬的
Director Wu, you strengthen the police force.
吴总监 你加强警力
Chief Li
李统领
Your gendarmes strengthen the law enforcement patrols.
你们宪兵加强执法巡逻
We are the Republic of China.
我们是中华民国
There rules and regulations we need to follow.
办事要讲法度
Students should not be allowed to disturb public order.
不能让学生扰乱社会治安
We also can't let foreigners, especially Japanese,
也不能让洋人 特别是日本人
to mock us that we have no ability to govern.
笑话我们没有执政能力
Ministry of Education and other functional departments.
教育部和其他各职能部门
Be firm on both daily operations and public statement clearly.
要态度坚决 立场鲜明
We should perform our duties firmly.
要坚定地履行自己的职责
A presidential decree will be issued tomorrow morning.
明天早上就要颁布总统令
The capital city is the crucial place.
京师乃首善之区
Assemblies, parades and speeches are strictly prohibited.
严禁集会游行 演说
Spreading leaflets and other social agitation.
散布传单等社会激切行为
will be strictly inspected by civil and military officers.
严令文武长官严密稽查
If any of the precedent circumstances occurs again,
如再有前项情事
do everything you can to stop it.
务当悉力制止
For those who refuse to obey,
其不服制正者
countermeasures shall be made according to law to ease chaos.
即应依法逮力 以遏乱萌
The president also said
大总统还说
we can't be all tough and strict.
也不能都来硬的
We can't push too hard.
霸王硬上弓是不行的
The general principle to solve this mess is four words,
解决这次乱局的总原则就四个字
tough but also gentle.
软硬兼施
Which we need to have further discussion about.
我们需要好好研究研究
As for implementation,
至于说到落实
I don't need to instruct you as you all know how to play it tough.
硬的你们都会 我就不用多说了
Just submit your plan.
把实施方案呈报上来就行了
But there must be a limit of hardness.
但是 硬也要有个度
Where should we draw the line?
何为度
Can I arrest people?
我抓人行不行
I'm only talking about principles.
我只是讲原则
It's your business on how to carry out.
那是你的事
You're slick.
你这是耍滑头
That's crime of omission.
得判你读职罪
Director Wu
吴总监
If you can really send me to prison now
你要是真的能把我送进监狱
to aviod all these,
躲过这一劫
I will thank you from the bottom of my heart.
我还真得要给你烧高香了
What do you mean?
你什么意思
Come on, don't bicker.
行了 都别斗嘴了
The president's order is clear.
大总统的意思已经很明确了
Arrest and punishment when needed.
该抓的抓 该打的打
Your Ministry of Education has to be tough too.
你们教育部也得强硬起来啊
We can't be all tough.
光来硬的不行
If that's the case,
如果只来硬的
it won't be the carrot and stick.
还叫什么软硬兼施啊
Then what's there to discuss about?
那还让我们研究什么呀
You can be gentle, I will not.
软的你来 老子不会
I can't do it alone.
光我也不行
It depends on everyone's cooperation.
要靠大家配合嘛
Do you have any good ideas?
你能有什么好的办法吗
Three
三条
First, all schools have an early holiday.
一是呢 让各个学校提前放假
Second, announce the higher-rank civil service examination.
二呢 宣布文官高等考试
Third, have spies
这第三嘛 让一些密探和特务
merge into the student groups,
打进学生内部
and to break their organization from inside.
做好策反工作
See.
你看 你看 你看
Don't we have the gentle approach now?
这软的方案不就有了吗
I say we adopt what mayor just said.
我觉得就按京兆尹说的力
The first two shall be implemented by the Ministry of Education.
第一第二条由教育部负责落实
The third one,
第三条
Director Wu is in charge.
吴总监 由你负责落实
good
好
Don't you have many spies under your command?
你手下不是有很多密探吗
Spend money when you should.
该花钱的时候就花钱
Spend some money, have spies work.
花点钱 让他们策反去
You are gonna give me the funds?
这钱你花
Dismiss.
散会
All principals of each school shall work with the staff,
着令各校校长会同教职员
supervise all students to attend classes within three days.
于三日内督率学生一律上课
Violators will be dismissed.
违反者一律遣散 开除
What's the situation? Dismissal
什么情况 开除
It seems that since the note from Japanese Ambassador,
看来自小照会之后
Beiyang government has chose to act hard.
北洋政府就动硬的了
The Ministry of Internal Affairs issued instructions to the Metropolitan Police Department.
内务部对京师警察厅发出训令
Require all police agencies in Beijing
要求北京各警察机构
strictly ban the trend of exclusion of Japan.
严格取缔排风潮
Not only that, just this morning
不光如此 就在今天上午
Dongcheng student lecture group
东城学生演讲团
had an altercation with Japanese soldiers.
与吕本兵发生口角
They were arrested by the police for that.
居然还遭到了警察的拘捕
arrest?
拘捕
Many students.
了好多学生
Classmates
同学们
I heard that Xu Shichang has given orders to Beijing
我听说徐世昌已经给北京
and other provinces.
及各省下达命令
That all public speech, march and protest
要求聚众 游行 演说
along with spreading leaflets are to be stopped.
散布传单等情事 悉力制止
Violators are arrested according to law.
违反者依法逮力
Are we at fault?
我们有错吗
No wonder it's not just the police today.
怪不得今天不光是警察
Even infantry and cavalry appeared on the streets.
连步兵和马队都上街了
They are not only arrogant,
而且见人就打 气焰十分器张
they also hit people with no good reasons.
太过分了 还打人
Classmates
同学们
I heard from Zhong Xie,
我听仲解说
All organizations and unions in Peking University
我们北大各个组织 刊物
have made an unanimous resolution.
以及社团一致决议
We are not doing as the Ministry of Education instructed.
决不执行教育部
This order to resume classes in three days.
关于三内的复课训令
Classmates who took part in the strike,
我们所有参加罢课的同学
You can take all your books and luggage,
可以将我们的书籍 行李
pack up,
收拾整齐
Once the government enforces the dissolution order forcefully
一旦政府强力执行解散令
We will leave school.
我们就离开学校
Find another way to save the country
另谋救国之路
Yeah, we'll find another way to save the country.
对好好我们另谋救国之路
Exactly!
没错
You don't know.
你们是不知道
Now everytime I go to vege market,
我现在只要一去菜市场
Auntie Wu says that
那吴妈看见我就说
Mrs. Chen, come on, come on.
陈夫人 快来快来
All these I put aside for you.
我给你包圆儿
I'm almost a cucumber dealer now.
我都快成黄瓜贩子了
Yannian
延年
Qiaonian
乔年
come over
过来
You two
你们两个再去一趟
go to Honglou Library of Peking University
北大红楼图书馆
Bring the mimeograph machine here again.
把油印机再搬来
This note to the Japanese ambassador
今天必须把这篇对于日使照会
and comment on the phone call by General Duan must be printed today.
及段督办通电的感言印发出来
Let the ten-people group spread it out tomorrow.
明日交由十人团散发
Be sure to let the people see clearly.
一定要让国民看清楚
Japan's greedy desire
日本的狼子野心
and this government's traitorous behaviour.
还有政府卖国的嘴脸
Go, go, go
快去 快去
Yes
好
Yannian Qiaonian
延年 乔年
I will go too.
我也去
What's wrong?
我说你是怎么搞的
You are always sending the children out in the middle of night.
总是大半夜支使孩子们出去
I'll go and see
我去看看
Don't.
你就别去了
There are policemen out everywhere now.
现在外边都是警察
But they
可是他们
Six more were arrested in Peking University just this morning.
今天早上北大又抓了六个
Do you have any idea
你知不知道
Yu zhengting
于正庭
Yannian
延年
What are you printing so late?
这么晚了印什么呢
We are going to the Hong Lou.
我们要去红楼
Give these newly printed leaflets
把这些刚印好的宣传单
to Fu Sinian and Luo Jialun.
给傅斯年还有罗家伦他们送过去
Why are you here so late?
你们这么晚怎么来了
Isn't the ten-people group going to preach on the street tomorrow?
明天不是十人团要上街宣讲吗
How can they have time to do this now?
他们俩怎么有工夫千这个事啊
You can't disobey your teacher's order.
师命不可违啊
Need to go.
我先走了
Peking University is moving to Shanghai?
北大要迁到上海啊
When did this happen?
什么时候的事啊
Sir
先生
What are you doing at school at this late hour?
这么晚了 还来学校干吗呢
How can Peking University move to Shanghai?
这北大怎么要迁到上海啊
Yes, if you move Peking University to Shanghai,
对啊 把北大迁到上海
It's not Peking University, it will be called Shanghai University.
就不应该叫北大 应该叫上大
It doesn't matter what the school is called now.
现在学校叫什么不重要了
Beijing is a political vortex.
北京就是一个政治的旋涡
One sneeze at the presidential palace,
总统府打一个喷嚏
school here will have an earthquake.
学校就会闹地震
People can't settle down to learn at all.
大家根本没法安心下来做学问
After the school moved to Shanghai
学校搬到上海以后
Leave this political vortex.
离开这个政治旋涡
It is beneficial to the development of the school.
对学校发展是有利的
Isn't this more important?
这个更重要吧
I have something to do. I'll go first
我手里还有事 我先走了啊
Goodbye, sir.
先生再见
go
走
Have you done using the mimeograph machines?
同学 油印机用完了吗
Can we borrow it?
我们能不能借一下
Bai Lan
白兰
Go inside and sleep. Don't sleep here.
进屋睡吧 别在这儿睡
Let me wait for them to come back.
我等他们回来吧
Why don't you go rest?
师母要不你先去休息
I'll just wait here.
我在这儿等着就行了
No, no.
不用不用
I'll stay.You go sleep.
我等就行了 你进屋睡吧
They came back.
他们回来了
They are back
回来了
I'm worried sick.
急死我了
You haven't slept yet?
您还没睡觉呢
I'm waiting for you. I'm afraid something will happen to you
等你们呢 怕你们出事
Your dad fell asleep after carving the pattern plate.
你爸刻完钢板就睡着了
Bai Lan and I dare not sleep.
我跟白兰不敢睡
You are back.
才回来
Something happened in Hong Lou?
是红楼有事吗
Mr. Hu Shi wrote a proposal about moving Peking University
胡适先生写了一份把北京大学
to Shanghai.
搬迁到上海去的倡议书
Himself and
他还亲自带
Fu Sinian, Luo Jialun went to mimeograph.
傅斯年和罗家伦几个同学去油印
We have been waiting for them to finish printing.
我们一直在等他们印完
What?
什什么
Proposal for moving Peking University to Shanghai?
把北大迁到上海的倡议书
Who initiated it?
谁倡议的
I took a copy for you to have a look.
我拿了一份您看看
Did Hu Shi take the wrong medicine?
这个胡适之是不是吃错药了
What's he thinking?
他怎么想的
Such important matter.
这么重要的事情
Why he didn't discuss it with me?
为什么不跟我商量一下
Move Peking University to Shanghai.
把北大迁到上海去
What's this nonsense?
这不是胡闹吗
Things here in Beijing has just begun to see some lights.
这北京的好戏刚刚开始
Is he tearing it down ?
是要谢幕拆台吗
Yannian
延年
Go get him for me.
你去 把他给我叫过来
In the middle of the night, you called someone to lecture.
深更半夜的你把人叫过来训话
It's not appropriate.
不太合适吧
It's literally the practice of feudal paternalism.
简直就是封建家长制的做法嘛
Just do as I say.
我让你叫你就去叫
Stop this nonsense.
你扯这些没用的干什么
It's people's freedom to have a proposal and to print articles.
提倡议 印文章那是人家的自由
You can disagree.
你可以不同意
But you have no right to interfere with people's freedom.
但是你无权千涉人家自由
He's making it hard for all of us.
他这是釜底抽薪
Why can't I interfere?
我凭什么不能干涉
Are you going or not?
你到底去不去
I won't go.
我不去
He is a professor at Peking University like you,
他跟你一样都是北大教授
not your sidekick.
又不是你的跟班
Why should he listen?
凭什么听你的话呀
Isn't it too hurtful of you to do so?
你这样做是不是太伤人了
Fine
好
I don't need you.
我不用你
I'll go by myself
我自己去
Get out of the way.
你给我起开
Uncle Chen, don't be angry.
陈伯伯 您别生气
Yannian is for your own good.
延年是为了您好
Yannian is just worried.
延年就是担心
If it gets ugly between you and Uncle Hu,
一您跟胡叔叔闹僵了
it will affect the student movement.
会影响到学生运动
It will hurt you even more.
更会伤到您自己啊
What does he know?
他懂个屁
This is shaking the army's morale.
动摇军心
Pulling the last straw!
功亏一
Let's start.
干活
Sir
先生
Where is Shi Zhi?
适之呢
Why are you here, Mr. Chen?
陈先生 您怎么来了
Professor Hu has gone home.
胡教授已经回家了
His house.
我去他家里找他
Why you going his house?
你去他家千什么
They have new born at home.
人家家里头有刚满月的孩子
I want to ask him.
我就是要问问他
Why does Hu Shi want to be a traitor?
他胡适之为什么要当叛徒
come on
来来来
Let's sit down and talk
咱们坐下说
come
来
Sit down
坐下说
I can't.
我坐不下
Look at what's written here.
你们看看 这写的是什么
Do you know?
你们知道
The result of Shizhi doing this?
适之这么做的结果是什么吗
Division!
制造分裂
Mr. Zhongfu
仲甫先生
Mr. Hu is doing so for a good cause.
胡先生这么做也是好心
He doesn't want the government...
他不想政府
Stupid
糊涂
We are the frontline, by doing this
大敌当前 你们这么做
is only leads to break the morale and divert attention.
是瓦解军心 转移视线
It's helping the traitors.
帮卖国贼的忙
As a result, it is inevitable that we will suffer and the enemy will laugh.
结果必然是亲者痛 仇者快
Sir.
先生
This kind of flyer
这种宣传单签名信
not even one can be seen.
一份都不能发
Destroy them all, all.
都给我销毁 通通销毁
Sir
先生
We really need to talk to Mr. Hu about this.
这事要不还是问一下胡教授
We can't bear this responsibility.
我们实在是负不了这个责任
You don't have. I'm responsible for this.
不用你负责任 我来干
You are only responsible for take Hu Shi here for me.
你只负责把胡适给我叫过来
Brother Zhongfu, don't be so impulsive, okay?
仲甫兄 你别这么冲动好不好
If I don't be impulsive,
我再不冲动
our hard-earned revolutionary achievements
我们辛苦累积的革命成果
is all going to be destroyed.
就要毁于一旦了
China, even the whole world now
全中国 甚至全世界
Are looking at our Peking University.
都在看着我们北大
Moving Peking University at this time
你们这个时候把北大要迁走
is to blow the candle and kill the revolution.
就是吹灯拔蜡扼杀革命
Such a simple truth.
这么浅显的道理
Can't you see clearly?
你们看不明百吗
Do you want to be Zhang Zongxiang, Cao Rulin
你们要做曹汝霖 章宗祥
or Lu Zongyu?
跟陆宗舆
Or do you want to help the Japanese?
还是要做日本人的帮
Hurry up and have Mr. Shizhi here.
赶快 把适之先生请来
Yes
是
Let's talk inside.
咱们进去说
Move out, destroy, move out
搬出去销毁 搬出去
Destroy it all.
销毁 全部销毁
Let's talk.
走进去说 进去说
Move!
搬出去
Liu Mei, any dried one?
柳眉 还有干了的吗
Yeah, I'll bring it to you later.
有一会儿给你拿过来啊
Qiaonian
乔年
Take this printed one away quickly.
你把这印完的赶紧拿走
One second.
等会儿
How's it going? Close to finish?
怎么样 忙差不多了吧
Mrs. Chen
师母
Auntie
姨妈
Have some porridge.
来喝点粥吧
My hands are too dirty.
师母我手太脏了
I won't help you this time.
就不帮你了
It's okay. I brought handkerchief.
没关系 我带了手帕
Clean then eat.
一会儿你们擦好了再吃
It's okay.
没事 姨妈
We're almost done.
我们快完事了
Your Dad, what can I do about him.
你说说 你们爸爸真是
He's not coming back this late at night,
这么晚了也不回来
but keeps you guys busying until now.
让你们儿个忙到现在
I'm used to that already.
他这样对我早习惯了
But he doesn't have the right to treat Uncle Hu like that today.
但是他今天凭什么对人家
So bossy.
胡适叔叔这么霸道
That's who he is, your Dad.
你爸爸就是这个秉性
Overly confident and a control freak.
刚自用 天马行空
Nobody can manage him.
谁也管不了他
I'm used to him offending people everywhere.
还到处得罪人 我也习惯了
But you have to believe,
你要相信
your father didn't do it for himself.
你爸爸不是为了自己
He did it for everyone.
他是为了大家
His heart is full of bigger things.
他心里装的都是大事
I understand all of this.
您说这些我都明白
But he always has this temper.
但是他老是这个脾气
How can it work?
怎么能行呢
I have read a western proverb.
我看过西方的一个谚语
Habit determines character, character determines fate.
说习惯决定性格 性格决定命运
He will suffer a big loss sooner or later.
他这样早晚要吃大亏
Yannian
延年
Sometimes
有时候
I really think you are so much like your father.
我真觉得你跟你爸爸太像了
You two always are against each other.
总是针尖对麦芒的
Auntie
姨妈
I'm nowhere as blunt as he is.
我有他那么冲吗
Shouchang
守常
I really can't understand.
我真的不能理解
Why did Shizhi do this?
适之为什么要这么做
Why would he?
他为什么要这么做
Actually, before Yannian came,
其实延年来之前啊
Shizhi and I have already argued.
我和适之已经争论过了
He has his ideas.
他有他的想法
He is afraid that the Beiyang government will take the ruthless way
他害怕北洋政府真的敢下毒手
and disband Peking University.
把北大给解散了
Arrest you and me.
把你我给抓起来
So he said he was thinking for you.
所以他说他是为你考虑
Think for me.
为我考虑
What does that mean?
什么意思
He feels that Peking University has made too many enemies now.
他觉得现在北大树敌太多
And get caught deeply in the current political vortex.
又深陷在眼下这个政治旋涡里
If there is one spark ignites,
但凡有个火星燃起来
Peking University will be ruined.
北大就毁了
And we'll be ruined.
我们也就跟着毁了
He said it wasn't easy for us to get here today.
他说 我们走到今天不容易
We can't lose it all.
不能前功尽弃
So he felt that at this time
所以他觉得看这个时候
moving Peking University to Shanghai,
把北大迁到上海去
stay away from all the trouble,
远离这个是非之地
then we and Peking University will be relieved.
我们和北大就都解脱了
That's what he said?
他是这么说的
This is his story.
这是他的说辞
To me, he is wrong.
其实在我看来是他想偏了
Where he stands and the angle he takes to look at this are wrong.
思考问题的立场和角度错了
The relationship between the fate of a country and a individual is turned upside down.
把国家和个人命运的关系搞颠倒了
What is his stands and angle?
他是什么立场
What perspective?
什么视角
He thinks that Peking University should be
他认为北大就是应该
and only be a place of academic study.
是一个做学问的地方
It should not be mixed with politics.
不应该和政治夹杂在一起
Diplomatic disputes
外交纷争
national interests,
国家利益
at the end of the day, all these are the government's business.
归根到底它是政府该管的事
We can express our opinions,
我们可以发表意见
but we have our own duty to practice.
但是不能越代
I refuted him explicitly just now.
我刚才明确地驳斥了他
National sovereignty and interests are above all else.
国家的主权和利益高于一切
Primary and secondary cannot be mixed.
主次轻重不能混
Now is the crucial moment to boycott the Paris Peace Treaty.
现在正是抵制巴黎和约的关键时刻
At this specific time,
在这个节骨眼上
moving Peking University is nothing else but running away.
北大南迁无异于逃跑
I just can't imagine this.
我很难想象
A year ago, he was a hero.
一年前他还是一个豪气干云
A former anti-feudal fighter.
冲锋在前的反封建的斗士
In a flash, he becomes
转眼之间就变成了
this counsellor who hesitates on every move.
瞻前顾后畏缩不前的谋士
This kind of spirit he shows
此种精神
disqualifies him as the coach to the youths.
如何能担得起青年导师的名声
This can't be, Shouchang.
不行 守常
I'm going to find him.
我要去找他
I want to pull him back.
我要把他拉回来
I introduced him to Peking University.
他是我引荐到北大的
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄
I can't leave him like this.
我不能不管
Fu Sinian has already gone.
傅斯年已经去了
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄
Didn't Fu Sinian already go?
傅斯年不是已经去了吗
You don't have to be so impulsive
你不用这么冲动
It's the same for us to wait here.
我们在这儿等是一样的
What if you did something you would regret?
你要万一走岔了怎么力
You are angry.
你怒气冲
Shouchang
守常
Go back to the office and close the door.
回办公室 把门关上
Shizhi
适之
I had your proposal and signature letter
我把你的倡议书和签名信
all torn up.
都撕毁了
Do you know?
你知道吗
Yes.
我知道
Fu Sinian has already told me.
専斯年已经告诉我了
Burn the proposal and letters
别说你是把倡议书
as you want.
和签名信烧毁了
Even if you are burning down my home,
你就是把我胡适之的家烧毁了
I will not be angry at you.
我也是不能生气的
Why?
为什么
First, you are my teacher.
第一 你是我的恩师
My brother.
我的兄长
Second, you knew
第二 你明明知道
it's safer to leave now than to stay.
眼下离开要比留下更安全
You still burned it anyway.
你还是毅然决然地把它给烧掉了
You did this
你这么做
entirely out of the great interests of the country and the nation.
完全是出于国家和民族的大义
It's virtuous.
这是高风亮节
How can I be angry?
我怎么能生气呢
So you changed your mind?
那这么说你想通了
Fine.
好
First
首先
Shizhi, I want to thank you for thinking for me.
适之我要感谢你为我看想
But let me ask you something.
但是我要问问你
Now hundreds of thousands of students across the country
现在全国几十万的学生
they are on the move.
全都行动起来了
All China is in solidarity with Peking University.
全中国都在声援北大
At this time, you proposed to move Peking University.
这个时候你倡议把北大搬走
Peking University is gone.
北大走了
The center of the movement is gone.
运动的中心没了
Everyone's effort goes wasted.
大家努力白白浪费了
Guo Xingang died for nothing.
郭心刚的命白送了
No one can stop the Paris Peace Treaty anymore.
没有人可以再阻止巴黎和约
Have you ever thought about it?
你想过吗
Of course I have.
你说的这些我為能不知
But now the Beiyang government has put pressure onto us.
可是现在北洋政府已经来硬的了
Classes must be resumed within three days.
明令三日之内必须复课
If classes don't resume, we will be forcibly dissolved.
不复课就要强行解散
Let me ask you something too.
那我请问你
The dissolution and relocation of Peking University
北大的解散和搬迁
Among these two,
两者相比较
which one is more advantageous?
哪一个更有利
This Peking University in China,
北大是中国的北大
this first-class university in China.
全中国的一流大学
Why does it have to dissolve when Beiyang government says so?
凭什么它北洋政府说解散就解散
If Peking University is disbanded,
北大解散
ask the Chinese people if they will agree.
你问问中国的民众答不答应
Ask teachers and students,
北大的老师
will they accept that?
北大的学生们答不答应
Shizhi
适之
When did you become
你什么时候变成了一只
an obedient sheep of Beiyang government?
被北洋政府服的绵羊了
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄
Now that you've put it here.
既然你把话说到这儿了
I'm no longer concealing my feelings.
我也不再隐满我的观点了
I returned to China from America two years ago
两年前我从美国回到中国
in order to contribute to the new culture.
为的就是做好新文化
At that time, you said that
那时候你说了一句话
no talking about politics for twenty years,
二十年不谈政治
devoting yourself in inspiring people's minds.
一心致力于启发国民的思想
I think that exactly is the way
我认为这就是一个学者
the fundamental way for a scholar to love and save the nation.
爱国和救国的根本之道
Along that path,
在这条道上
every one of us in New Youth,
我们《新青年》的每一位同人
we made concerted efforts.
齐心协力
we made the new culture movement flourish.
把新文化运动搞得风生水起
We changed the once-lifeless old Peking University
把那个曾经死气沉沉的旧北大
We brought it alive again.
变得生机然
But then you changed.
可是后来你变了
You said the new culture movement could not be separated from politics.
你说新文化运动它离不开政治
You even said the New Culture Movement
你甚至说新文化运动
it is politics in itself.
它本身就是政治
What I want is not only the flourish of Peking University.
我要的不是北大的生机盎然
What I want is the flourish of China
我要的是中国的生机盎然
We can't get by not talking, not arguing, not fighting.
不辩 不争 不可以
What you said, what you want.
你说的去辩 辛去争
I can understand and I support it.
我都能理解我也支持
So.
所以
May Fourth Movement
五四运动
Students marched in the streets.
学生上街游行
Oppose the Paris Peace Treaty
反对巴黎和约
I sincerely support them.
我真心支持
In Shanghai
在上海
I was with Yannian and the others.
我还和延年他们一起
I attended the demonstration in person.
亲身参加了示威游行
But it's different now.
可是现在不同了
Students don't attend classes, professors don't teach.
学生不上课 教授不教书
All schools in Beijing have gone on strike.
整个北京的学校都罢课了
Everyone has gone to politics.
所有的人都去搞政治去了
The whole society is in chaos, brother Zhongfu.
整个社会都乱了 仲甫兄
Is this what you hope for?
难道这就是你陈仲甫
Is this the kind of flourish you want?
想看到的生机益然吗
We can't sit and wait for that to come, Shizhi.
生机益然不是等来的 适之
We have to fight for it.
是要斗争来的
There's no making without breaking
不破不立
China now needs warriors and fighters.
比时的中国需要勇士和斗士
Why do we Chinese can do nothing but just watch.
凭什么我们中国人要眼地
Watch the Paris Peace Treaty get signed.
看着签订巴黎和约
Why should we just watch the loss of Qingdao happening.
凭什么我们要眼地看着青岛
Giving it away to the Japanese without even arguing?
拱手让给日本人
Are we Chinese farm animals?
我们中国人
Shall we just wait for the knives to fall?
就应该像畜生一样等死吗
Certainly not
当然不是
Shall we just get slaughtered like farm animal?
就应该像畜生一样任人宰割吗
I'm not advocating not to fight
我不是主张不去抗争
I mean, we can't act foolhardy.
我的意思是我们不能蛮干
Our power is limited.
我们力量有限
We should know how to stay away from the mess
我们要懂得远离这些是是非非
and protect ourselves.
保护自己
The reason why I proposed to move Peking University
我之所以把北大提出来
to Shanghai.
要南迁上海
I want to keep Peking University untouched.
我为的就是要把北大保留下来
Where we have the campus,
留得青山在
where we can still have the classes.
不怕没柴烧
That's all.
我仅此而已
That is a compromise.
你这是妥协
It's surrender
是投降
The reason why China is so timid now.
中国之所以这么窝囊
We do not have enough people like Guo Xingang.
就是因为郭心刚太少
We have too many people like Hu Shi.
胡适之太多了